Inventory of the Benjamin Schwartz Papers, 1861-1868
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Benjamin Schwartz Papers 1861-1868
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
2007.01
14
Schwartz, Benjamin
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
This collection was purchased 01/05/2007.
Biographical Information
A Benjamin Swartz (alternate name: Benjamin F.Swartz), enlisted in the 5th Pennsylvania Calvary, Company F. His rank upon entering the regiment is listed as "Saddl.", his discharge rank was Sergeant.
Scope and Content
These letters are written from or on behalf of Benjamin Schwartz, who was stationed in Virginia with the 5th Pennsylvania Calvary, Company F. The letters primarily document a brother's concern over his family's health and money he sends to his sister. There is limited discussion of skirmishes, troop movement, taking and being taken prisoner, and recurrent predictions that the war will end soon. Schwartz mentions that the Union camp at Williamsburg, Virginia was burned by rebel forces.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in chronological order.
Contents List
- Series 1: Letters of Benjamin Schwartz 1861-1869
  - Item 1: Letter, Camp Griffin, to Sister Libby 11/23/1861
    "fixing up things to keep us a little warm" Went to two reviews, one at Bailey's Cross Roads.
  - Item 2: Letter, Camp Griffin, to Dear Sister 3/5/1862
  - Item 3: Letter, Williamsburg, to Dear Sister 11/21/1862
    Concerned about money sent, busy building winter quarters, notes that they have many new horses and recruits, predicts war will not last long.
  - Item 4: Letter, Williamsburg, to Dear Sister 4/23/1863
    Hard week, rebels burned Union camp, but repulsed them, captured a number of rebel prisoners.
  - Item 5: Letter, Williamsburg, to My Dear Sister 5/1/1863
    Predicts rebels will have to give up as "they are near starved[?] out and played out to nothing" "was taken prisoner and made my escape."
  - Item 6: Letter, Williamsburg, to My Dear Sister 6/10/1863
    Sending money.
  - Item 7: Letter, Portsmouth, Va. 2/25/1864
    Describes march to Richmond, foiled plan to burn city.
  - Item 8: Letter, Camp near Portsmouth 4/11/2864
    Their camp has moved many times.
  - Item 9: Letter, Camp near Portsmouth, To: My Dear Sister 4/26/1864
  - Item 11: Letter, Camp Near Jones Landing to My dear Sister Elizabeth Schwartz, North Buffalo, Erie County, N. Y. 8/21/1864
    Surprised that Home Guard was called out to defend Buffalo, describes prowess of Company F.
  - Item 12: Letter, Richmond to Dear Sister 4/29/1865
    The war is over.
  - Item 13: Letter, Sollomon City, Saline County, Kansas to Dear Sister 3/3/1869
    Discusses cold weather and high water. Folder also contains a single sheet, with paper and ink similar to letter above, asking for Henry's location, noting the loss of Eve's husband.
- Series 2: (Item 14) Letter of Henry F. Jackson, Deep Bottom, Va. 3/25/1865
  Stationery printed with "U. S. Christian Commission." handwritten underneath "and hard tack." Sent money, "Benjamin has gone out on a raid."
- Series 3: Envelopes
  - Item 15: envelope addressed to Miss. Elizabeth Schwartz, Williamsvill[e], Erie Co., New York 10/18/n.y.
  - Item 16: envelope addressed to Elizabeth Schwartz, Williamsville, Erie Co., N[ew] York 9/13/1862
  - Item 17: (month?) 27 1868
    Envelope addressed to Miss. Elizabeth Schwartz, Williamsville, Erie County, N. Y. has word "Coyote" written on it.